Hello everyone and welcome back to Agentic Thinking with Mike and Matthias.
We're back again for another great topic.
We're going to talk about some news items today.
The main topic for day is the Vibe coding trap.
Did you know that you were walking into a trap when you
were building Vibe coding things? I think this is a relevant article.
This is about AI and how it's potentially bankrupting early startups.
So this is an interesting article.
We're going to kind of unpack this today.
Matthias, how are you doing?
>> I'm doing great
and
yeah, excited to see what we come up with here.
We may well have different opinions.
Let's see what happens.
>> That makes just for good tv, you have different opinions about things.
So let's step into this one.
So without a whole bunch of ado here, let's just go into
the main topic here, which is this article which I will put.
It's a Medium article and Matthias, I don't get to see all
of the article because it is a subscriber only article here.
So if you want to go check this out, this is on
Medium is the article that we're kind of reviewing here, so you
should go check it out. The article is in the description, it's
also in the chat window as well here.
And I'm going to lead you, Matthias, to kind of give us
a little bit of a runup here on what's in the article
and why is this topic coming up now?
What's happening with startups with AI?
What's the trend here that's happening?
Go ahead and take it away.
>> Yeah, so I found that article and I thought that would be
a great one for us to go through because it's opinionated.
It resonates with me basically saying
businesses building on top of Vibe coded software and wipe coded products
apparently increasingly find themselves in quite a pickle.
You know, they
definitely manage very well to, you know, to produce hype and to,
to, to deliver and ship something that may well look appealing.
But when it comes to actually building a business on top of
such a software,
there may well be some traps, some bigger ones, some, some smaller
ones. And the article has a few very nice examples, you know,
around database corruption, missing database indexes, about
massive waste of tokens for AI applications, you know, when, when they
don't really engineer what they're actually sending back to the LLMs.
And plus obviously a number of security
issues, you know,
around
protecting, you know, anything you, you put put out as, as a
public website or so. So obviously some of the Stories are pretty
drastic and,
you know, probably represent
extreme poor and bad examples. But nonetheless, I think there's a lot
here to unpack in terms of our own experiences as well.
What have we seen, how do we feel about it?
And also, is it right to think of a dichotomy of vibe
coding on one end of the spectrum versus, I don't know, engineering
software engineering on the other end of the spectrum?
So I'll leave it here for now.
>> Yeah. So this is interesting to me.
I believe. So Microsoft did a very cool demo, I think in
the March timeframe. They had some users on a stage and they're
kind of talking about like, you know, how do we apply AI,
where do we apply it in our report writing or data engineering
process? What is this? What does AI look like in the hands
of a new engineer versus a seasoned engineer, which one would win?
And so they kind of pitted these AI pieces so a novice
engineer with AI in their hands and said, hey, go build this
report, go build this data. It's up to you to use the
AI with you to go build something the business may want.
And then they gave the same task to an engineer who, who
knows the program, knows how to build things, and said, go build
this equivalent information. So you got these kind of two worlds of
novice with AI and expert without.
And so they did this kind of demo of between.
Okay, we're going to give you two report pages.
Which one was built by the AI, which one was built by
the person, which one was built by the novice or the expert.
And so it was really interesting to watch.
It was somewhat hard to determine in certain scenarios, other places it
was very clear which one was which.
But at the end of the day, they were trying to bring
the parallel that bringing AI to a novice user helps you build
incredible things much faster. But you lose some of that expertise, that
knowledge around the experts in this space, which is throttling capacity management
using only the amount of information you need, things that you kind
of learn the hard way of building them on your own.
And so when you give AI to an expert who, who's a
really good developer, you actually get a compounding effect of really good
output from them. They're able to work faster.
All these edge cases. And I think partly to this article, which
is, right, it's alluding to, I believe, partly here around the single,
you know, it's the millionaire solopreneur, right?
I'm a single shop, I'm building my app, I'm developing it, and
then I just launched it on Production day.
And it goes well until the SQL database falls over.
It goes well until the API starts throttling.
And all these users who are now trying to use your app,
it's actually falling over. So had you been an engineer designing this,
you probably would have gotten to the same end result for an
app, but your infrastructure on the backend side would use some caching.
There'd be different API patterns, there might be different architectural decisions that
was being made to scale this to high volume.
Let me just pause right there.
Is this kind of where you feel this article is going, Matthias,
or is there a different vibe that this article is pushing in?
>> Well,
okay, so one thought that I just had as you were talking,
and I think that's actually where the article is going, I'm not
decided yet. And maybe we can discuss that whether there actually is
a really strict distinction between
sort of a seasoned engineer architecting something and then building a system
with the help of AI on the one hand, as opposed to,
you call it a novice user or sort of someone who doesn't
approach that from an engineering standpoint and who basically
gives all the powers to the AI.
Basically, Vibe codes the whole thing, right?
AI makes the decisions.
The article obviously says if it's the latter,
you're bound to get into some trouble.
You know, maybe minor, maybe major, may be so bad that ultimately
it bankrupts your business because, you know, you may well have launched
well, but you haven't been able to then actually scale the thing
or secure it or make it as cost efficient as it should
be. Right.
So what I'm wondering now is if we're saying there is this
inherent danger and threat and challenge from wipe coding, is that something
which is just a matter of time in the sense that, you
know, as new generations of models come out and as the tools
we're using to do the vibe coding get better is, you know,
are we just waiting for some iteration of AI where those problems
no longer exist? Or do we genuinely or always will have a
distinction where AI and LLM driven development can only go so far?
And we will always need, you know, for something that's really thorough
and scalable and secure and solid, will we always need
a well trained, well experienced engineer there?
Right. I think ultimately that's the big question we're faced with today.
And I'm not sure I'm keen to hear what you think, but
I'm not sure anyone has a definitive answer yet.
>> Let me add a parallel of something I've heard messaging messaged over
the last couple months. Let Me see, I may take a tangent
here, Matias. This may not be a tangent.
I don't know. There are some really strong experts in the Power
BI community,
namely SQL BI and Tabular Editor, which I think are very great
teams of people, extremely smart individuals, no discrete to any other acumen
in the Power BI data modeling in space.
I feel like I've watched a shift occur where and I don't
think they were saying, to be very clear, these teams of people
were not saying no, don't use AI.
I think the initial rounds of AI interaction from Tabular Editor and
SQL BI were like, look, hold off.
The models are not quite good enough to handle what we're trying
to do. There still needs to be a human in the loop.
Don't just brain dump and let the AI try to build decks
and models and everything just willy nilly.
Right? So I think that part was clear.
But I feel like recently, in the last two to three weeks
I've seen an immense amount of recommunication around those teams now shifting
heavily into using AI. Tabular Editor is now coming out with a
CLI tool that's helping it become much more capable for building tymdal
and semantic models using agents. Much more structured information.
So the Tabular Editor team has built a harness around agents that
are making it very friendly to model development.
I think this is something they had to do because Power BI
had come out with the MCP modeling server.
Why would we need Tabular Editor if you have an MCP modeling
server and I can talk to an agent directly?
We've done this on the show, We've done a number of demos
here of talking to the agent model and say, build me a
diagram, change these measures, group these things together.
Why do I want to go talk to another third party tool
where I can directly talk to an agent, have it done faster,
not having to click any buttons.
I think there's been a shift here where these teams have had
to greatly adapt this one. I'm now seeing advertising from Marco Russo
and SQL BI saying, hey, we're now going to teach you how
to use DAX with agents. How does agents write dax?
What do we need to communicate to an agent so that it's
good at writing dax? These were not messages I was seeing three
months ago, four months ago. And so all what I'm trying to
say here and maybe bringing it back to your point here around
like where are things going? The models are getting much better.
The harnesses that people are developing are getting much more capable.
The large language models can Hallucinate can do weird things.
But what you want is you want a very accurate system around
a harness, wrangling that large language model to allow it to reason,
to allow it to build things that are useful.
But it needs to be able to test.
It needs to have specifications. These have linting built into it.
Did it even write the right syntax that goes into the DAX
statement or not? Right. So these are things, I think, that are
trying to be organized in the community right now.
And we're seeing a shift where more and more experts are adopting
AI and building tools around it, which is making it more useful
for everyone. So now back to this point here.
This is where we are today.
I think these models are going to continue to get better.
The harnesses will continue to get more capable.
People are going to continue to build better tools that are going
to enable better usage of this moving forward.
And so while I think we're going to have some users here.
Right. I'm going to rapidly build an app.
It may fall over, it may break on the back end.
Okay. Shame on me. I'm a new user to Vibe coding this
whole application thing. But it doesn't take long for you to realize,
oh, it wasn't that the AI couldn't build, was more that your
prompts and what you described to the AI was insufficient.
And I think that's much more of the scenario here, which is
we just have people not being able to prompt correctly into the
AI to get out what they want.
And I know this because, Matthias, you're putting me to shame.
I'm doing a certain amount of programming and Vibe coding and building
apps, and I probably wouldn't call it Vibe code anymore.
I would really want to call it, like, agentically coding, because I
kind of know what I want to build.
But, Matthias, you're building things well above my pay grade, way better
than what I'm doing. Much more elaborate and complex.
But you're using agents to do a lot of the development.
But that's because your system that you've been working on and developing
is just so well done. And it's incredible, like, what it can
do. And so I think the more the general population and public
starts learning what this looks like in people, building programs and applications
that help this to become more real, it's just going to shift
my work away from clicking buttons and moving things around to describing
things to an agent and having it pair program, or pair build
with me alongside here. So let me just pause.
I'm gonna just leave that thought there for a moment.
What do you think about that?
Is that, is that alignment with where you're thinking things are going
to.
>> Okay, so I think one thing we can take for granted is
today, with the harnesses and models we have available to us, you
can build very, very, very substantial, complex
tools and software applications. Right. If.
Right. Big. If
you know what to ask for.
If you basically do
a fair amount of the architecture upfront and then feed that into
the prompt. As you just said,
prompting is what it's all about.
Yes, but
are we ever going to get to a point where you're going
to get similar outputs from an AI without having to do that
kind of upfront work? That's really what I wonder about.
Right. Because that would basically mean that we no longer have a
wipe coding trap to go back to the article.
Right. And so I don't think we will ever get there.
If you want to believe all the big players and the anthropics
and openais in this world who want to sell you their tokens
for lots of money, obviously they make you believe that you just
do voice input to a dot or a bot or whatever you
want to call it, and then they build the next million dollar
business for you. Yes. Without you holding any hands.
Right. Yeah. I am very, very, very skeptical about that.
But
on the other hand, I'm extremely excited about the capabilities we have
with the current generation of models,
you know, allowing you to actually build, architect and build very substantial
systems and applications
for very, very cheap and very, very quickly, you know, so.
Yeah. Do you just pushing it back to you.
Do you think I'm wrong with my skepticism?
Do you think this is just a matter of evolution?
>> I, I think we're in the middle of the evolution process of
this. Right. I, I think if we look at, if I look
at where things have come from January till now,
in January through maybe March, I was doing a lot of experimentation.
I was building very small, rough versions of applications.
I feel like now I'm spending a lot more time polishing and
getting something that was way closer to a real production item that
I would want to put my name on and put out the
door as branded items.
I only see this progression moving further towards.
It's going to get more capable, we're going to get better models,
we're going to get more use out of these models for us
as we build things. So I feel like the progression is moving
towards. In the same way I made the analogy on the Explicit
Measures podcast, in the same way that Power BI reports were democratized
for the Business user, the BI team, we're democratizing application and app
development by using agents to do the same thing.
I don't have to go into a Power BI report and ask
or figure out how to write D3.
The visuals all run on D3.
I just take for granted that there's a framework around it.
And when I click the button to make a bar chart, boom,
bar chart shows up, I drag my fields, boom.
It all maps together. Someone spent a lot of work around this
to make it an easy experience to use.
They democratize all the code that was required to write that.
In the same way, I see agents being that Power BI like
tool that democratizes the app.
Because some users are able to build apps and scale them in
systems, right? You may not be able to and that I think
that's more of a limitation on your knowledge around what does an
at scale app look like? How do you communicate to the edit?
So you know, for example, when you're doing a planning mode around
what your app may be or what design you may be building,
you say, look, I need this app to be able to be
scalable, right? So some of the prompt that I should be presenting
to it is this app needs to be scalable.
It needs to have these types of design features on the back
end. You can describe more of those features, the AI will return.
Hey Matthias, for building your app, did you know you need a
redis cache? If you don't understand what a redis cache is and
why that helps your SQL Server not fall over or your API
not throttle because you're hitting the same request over and over again.
If you don't understand that, then how can you tell it, yes,
I need it or no I don't, right?
>> You.
>> Now what is really is interesting here is you can say things
like you, you have to learn how to use language of like,
you know, I'm going to have again, it's, it's good, clear requirements,
right? When I'm building the app, I got to be able to
tell my, even my developers today, right?
If I told you, Matias, I'm going to Build app for 10
people, you would have in your mind a certain kind of architecture.
And then you would ask me questions around like, well, how often
is the data going to be accessed?
How much data are we accessing?
Is this just a little bit or a lot of bit, right?
That will change part of how you design the solution.
But you already know this because of your historical experience.
You've gone into these problems and ran into a wall and how
to solve it. The AI knows how to solve these problems.
I'm just not telling it the right requirements.
And so I think that's where things for me, I'm like, I'm
looking at this now and saying, I think the AIs now are
really good and they can outbuild what I am aware of or
what I'm knowledgeable about. And so now I have to direct the
agents. And
one area that I'm going to say is very hard to do,
and even I struggle with this
sometimes My team asks me questions from the AI because they'll talk
to it and they'll have an answer and they'll respond back.
It gives you two options that are very close in capability.
Right. How do I have a preference to push the AI one
direction versus another?
>> Right, right.
>> What, what knowledge or background information do I have that helps me
design the solution for what I want?
And so sometimes the AI will come back to you with two
choices that are probably both good in their own right.
But maybe a downstream design solution feature that you want to build
may conflict with these two items or this decision point.
Right. And. And that's where I think the expertise of the expert
starts coming into play. You're able to kind of zoom out a
little bit more, look a bit.
A bit of a big picture, figure out what's going on, and
then zoom into the very specific details of what the agent's asking
for and then catering your prompt better to what they need.
I'm hearing you say yes, so it, it feels like maybe this
is something you've encountered with your agents where it's giving you two
good options, but you got to pick one.
>> Oh, yeah, yeah. That's definitely something which resonates.
Generally you get more than two.
And I generally, my experience, you generally have a recommendation as well.
When there are choices to make.
Oftentimes the agent highlights what they would recommend, but I recognize what
you say.
Oftentimes I would then push back and say, can you present the
options in a different language? Can you dumb it down?
Or can you explain what the impact will be?
You know, things like that, and that normally actually helps.
Or another way to go would be for me to say,
I don't care. I've put you in charge of delivering this goal.
You make the call. As long as you achieve the strategic goals
I set out with you in the beginning, you are free to
do whatever you want. You know, so that would be another approach.
I think ultimately it's about being selective.
You know, what component do you care so deeply about that you
get very hands on and that you get very involved with the
architecture and what component doesn't need that where you basically where you
can afford to hand it off to an agent in terms of
making decisions. Right.
>> That's interesting. I like that idea of like there are definitely parts
of the application or whatever you're building where you're going to be
very stringent on. Like it has to be this way.
This is the vision I have.
>> Yeah. Like, you know, identity authentication, payments, you know.
>> Yes.
>> You know, that kind of sort of hard currency stuff.
Yes. But do not mess it up.
UX or Docs or.
Yeah, anything. Anything that's sort of more cosmetic rather than
ultimately it's, you know, again, coming back to the article which obviously
says if you're just wipe coding, you may well be able to
start a business, but you know, don't be surprised if it goes
bankrupt. Right. At the end of the day it's, it's, it's a
risk assessment. Right. And you want to think about what's the risk
of the AI getting this particular piece wrong.
If, if that's a risk you're not willing to accept, then you
better get more hands on here and you better get more involved.
Right.
>> I like that part. Yes. I think it's a good, I think
it's a good litmus test of like, you know, if the AI
broke this part, would it be a problem?
So again, to this article going back maybe here a little bit
to this one and talking more about it, which is, you know,
where does the artist, where does the, the author here start picking
on, hey, where should we be putting our pressure?
Right? Some of our pressure should be on like the database design,
the API design, telling the agent to build tests around high volume
capacity. Right. I mean this is, these are part of the techniques
I think that we would apply here and from those techniques that
would then elevate more of our design.
Right. We can still rely on the agent to build it, but
telling it better requirements will change the design so that it is
using caching. It is not letting the SQL database fall over.
And maybe to some degree here, unless there's, I mean most of
this is,
I feel like most of this is fixable.
Like if you, if you did go down the route and you're
gonna, you're gonna burn some users and you know, the people are
gonna adopt the app and the app starts crashing, okay, fine.
There's very little that you can do that is unrecoverable.
At least quickly building through okay.
Hey, agent. My SQL database is falling over for these reasons.
What's going on? That's a really good.
Now that you know the problem, you go back to the agent
and say, build the monitoring, build the error messaging that we need
build. And you can rapidly iterate through these problems.
And so while it was quick to build the app, you also
have another agent. I think people forget this.
There's an assistant that's there to help you debug them too, and
figure out better architectures. And as fast as it was to create
the original app, you probably could recode that with another agent to
fix it.
>> Most of it is recoverable, except for one thing, and that's very.
>> I want to say, security here.
>> No, no.
>> Okay.
>> Business model.
>> Oh.
>> If you made assumptions and launched a business, you know, with.
With a. So with a pricing model or so.
Or with certain sort of contract types.
Yeah. And then it turns out that is never going to be
profitable.
>> Yeah.
>> You're in the pickle. And the article has some examples for that
as well. Right. That's a great.
That's something you can't really recover from
>> if you're charging too little for the app you're using in.
The app is very expensive. It'll never work.
>> Which, if you don't mind, leads us quite nicely to open AI,
which we covered last week because they've just had a similar realization.
You know, they've. They've had a.
A $200 max subscription.
>> Yeah.
>> For a long time. Which they put on pause at some point.
And last week they launched a new 500 plan, you know, bigger
than any of their. Of their competitors.
Yeah. And they also brought back the 200 plan, but with substantially
reduced quotas in. In within the tour.
Sorry, I think I'm about to.
Good. Sorry, I was. Didn't want to sneeze into the microphone.
So they got a lot of heat for that from people who.
Who were on the $200 plan suddenly being told, well, you can
stay on it, but we're reducing what you're getting out of it
by 50% or so.
It's definitely not going down very well.
But that is an example where something like that happened.
And obviously we've seen that with respect to the cost of using
AI getting
increasing continuously. That's something we talked about a few times.
June 26th was a big deal when Copilot completely changed their pricing
model.
Companies like that can get away with that to some degree, but
you are small business. May not be.
>> This, I think, is way more impactful because now that you have
this,
I feel like they're slowly cooking the frog here in this example,
right? You're, you're getting value at 40 bucks a month.
Okay, great. We're, we're starting to throttle you.
We're starting to get some limitations.
You're getting too many tokens used, right?
Okay, well we're going to move you up to like $100 a
month plan. Okay, great. Now everyone starts doing $100 a month plans.
Okay. And then we have this transition to.
Okay, well in the business world, right, we're going to transition you
away from monthly user plans and we're going to transition you into
pay as you go kind of plan.
So now there's this whole new realm of pay as you go
and tokens become more important. And now we're getting even more premier
models. And so now we've gone from 200amonth all the way up
to 500amonth for these plans. And you know, if you're a team
of three people, okay, 200 to 500, yes, it's a hit on
your business line. But if you're providing value and adding value from
that, okay, not that major of a hit.
If you're a Microsoft, if you're a SAP, if you're a big
organization and you're trying to, and you're trying to figure out how
to go from $200 per user to $500 per user to get
them to do what they're doing and you're cheapening out some of
these lower end plans and they're getting less tokens, they can't get
things done. You're starting to feel a pinch.
This is boiling the frog. We're starting to bring the price level
up for these higher amounts. And so the more you increase the
price on these plans to get more tokens out of them, I
think the harder people are going to search for optimization,
doing things efficiently, picking the right model for the right solution.
You know, this is what brings to mind the hydrofusion that, that
GitHub is coming out with. So hydrofusion is going to be Microsoft
solution to this, which is picking the right model mid prompt.
How do you pass context to agents or different models when they
need to be in Hydrofusion? So these are, these are areas that
I think are going to be more important moving forward.
>> Yeah, sorry, just got distracted.
>> No worries.
Do you have the 500amonth open AI plan?
Are you needing that one?
>> I don't know. I don't need that.
I use a combination of plans from different providers and
I use Some very sort of dynamic routing, let's put it that
way, when it comes to choosing the right provider, the right model,
the right effort level.
Yeah, that definitely took a lot of engineering and
experimentation as well because I don't like wasting money.
You know, I'd,
I'd, I'd rather keep the bill low, so.
Absolutely no. I never even got to the 200 plan either.
I don't need it.
They've also had, interestingly, you know, ever since the
big announcements from open air last week, interestingly, they've had
quite some trouble regarding performance in particular.
You know, it's definitely something which I've been following quite closely because
I actually use codecs and open AI.
>> Sure.
>> A lot of my day work, if
>> they go down, you can't use them.
You're seeing that.
>> I've definitely noticed massive performance degradations with respect to
speed and with respect to, you know, token flow.
Not necessarily around quality. Although. Although, you know, if you go online
you'll find quite a few people who claim that anything below Astra
is no longer as smart as it used to be.
I can't really judge that. I.
It's not necessarily my own experience, but there have been quite a
few outages where mid session models suddenly report that they're at capacity
and basically you need to retry and things like that.
It's not looking great, let's put it that way.
>> Yeah,
it feels like when these large models are announced and everyone gets
really excited about these new things, there's this level of usage that
happens, spike of usage that happens here that really pushes people over
the hill. So we hope open I, open AI can kind of
figure themselves out here. So one interesting article today.
Go check out the article if you can on medium.
It's really good. It's written by Abdul and I recommend go reading
that one. The Vibe coding trap why AI generated MVPs are quietly
bankrupting early stage startups. So there's some definitely considerations there as you
educate yourself on how you build apps and build things there.
That also being said, thank you Matias for a great conversation around
OpenAI and what's happening with their world and how we're seeing and
using AI in our workflows day to day.
That being said, thank you all so much and we'll end here
with a little treat for everyone as we end our episode today.
Thank you all and we'll see you next time.
>> Thank you and thanks everyone.
>> Jack from Finance builds his first report at night.
Experts might but his team sees the light.
Five minutes to wow when the room starts to leave.
Power be I rising
from the ground unseen.
One shore before the tower bow.
Jack from fin is pouring joy into.
Talk about crease can take a year to land.
Bottom up. Belief it's right in someone's head.
A colleague shares a fire,
the spark goes wild.
Adoption isn't force,
it's arising time.
Power now.
They said Surprise would choose another name
but the people on the desk still played the game
because the two felt close
because the wind fell near
bottom up
that's how the truth appears.
Don't wait for the mandate from a distant floor.
Start with the person who needed one door.
Give them five minutes and a reason to believe the rest of
the company love us to breathe.
There's a night festival the base under my chest.
Think of Jack and how the quiet ones progress.
Sam.
>> Agency thinking,
>> Agency thinking.